Guide to the History of Medicine artifacts collection, 1550-1980s RL.10155
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- George D. Wilbanks Collection Artifacts, approximately 1750-1952, over 90 items
  - Brass scales with weights, match holder, and prescriptions, undated (Artifact-box 260, Item hwilba0054)
    Wooden box with apothecary weights written on inside of the lid. Twenty-three manuscript prescriptions on small separate pieces of paper.
  - Alcohol lamp in chrome box, undated (Artifact-box 266, Item hwilba0055)
    Stamped on bottom: U.S.A. M.D. Pioneer, New York, NY. Used to dissolve powders and pills into solution for injection.
  - Knife case with knives, retractor, needle and catheter, undated (Artifact-box 267, Item hwilba0056)
    Leather case.
  - Miscellaneous surgical instruments, 19th century (Artifact-box 283, Item hwilba0057)
    Includes: Slide-catch forceps, folding scalpel, needles, scoop.
  - Miscellaneous medical instruments, 19th and 20th centuries (Artifact-box 3, Item hwilba0058, Artifact-box 332)
    Includes: Hale's speculum, syringes, D&C set, anesthesia mask for use with ether or chloroform, amputating knife, forceps, plastic endocervical applicators, retractors, dilators.
  - Octagonal scarificator, undated (Artifact-box 21, Item hwilba0059)
    Has 16 blades in brass case.
  - Metal pharmaceutical box, undated (Artifact-box 342, Item hwilba0061)
    Leavenworth Kansas: Adolf Lance. Label.
  - Wollaston-type brass optometer, 19th century (Artifact-box 338, Item hwilba0062)
    One lens can be changed in eyepiece. Used to measure sight and fit eyeglasses.
  - Boston-style doctor's bag with instruments, undated (Artifact-box 343, Item hwilba0063, Artifact-box 337)
    Bag is made of leather. Contents include: two small surgical kits, needles and syringes, one syringe in metal case.
    Artifact Box 337 contains doctor's bag, Artifact Box 343 contains the instruments.
  - "Patented" wooden tonic cup, undated (Artifact-box 341, Item hwilba0064)
    Wood used in cup reputedly had medicinal properties to enhance any solution drunk as a tonic.
  - Contemporary fetoscope, 20th century (Artifact-box 32, Item hwilba0065)
    Steel. London: Down. Used in the U.K. and developing countries.
  - Porcelain crucible, undated (Artifact-box 321, Item hwilba0066)
  - Brass speculum, undated (Artifact-box 340, Item hwilba0067)
  - Glass mortar and pestle, undated (Artifact-box 324, Item hwilba0068)
    Heavy blown glass.
  - Wooden mortar and pestle, undated (Artifact-box 330, Item hwilba0069)
  - Pewter infant feeder, undated (Artifact-box 320, Item hwilba0070)
    Hallmark on bottom of bowl.
  - Pewter infant or invalid feeders, undated (Artifact-box 328, Item hwilba0071)
    Five pewter infant or invalid feeders. Reproductions.
  - Wooden fermentation jar with lid, undated (Artifact-box 323, Item hwilba0072)
    Wire handle.
  - Barber surgeon-style bleeding bowl, 17th century? (Artifact-box 155, Item hwilba0073)
  - Oxygenkure oxygen generator, late 19th-early 20th century (Artifact-box 363, Item hwilba0074)
    Oxygenkure oxygen generator machine. New York: Seeger & Clarke. Box with directions on the inside of cover.
  - Steam atomizer, undated (Artifact-box 69, Item hwilba0075)
    Whitall, Tatum & Co. Two glass cups, alcohol lamp; brass and wood.
  - Doctor's saddlebag, early 19th century (Artifact-box 78, Item hwilba0076)
    Saddlebag has space for bottles and a drawer on each side. Leather with brass trim. Glass bottles, many with contents.
  - Anatomy dissection kit, 20th century (Artifact-box 203, Item hwilba0077)
    Housed in a rolled case. Used by Dr. Wilbanks in his 1952 anatomy class.
  - Medicine chest, undated (Artifact-box 45, Item hwilba0078)
    Medicine chest with homeopathic medicine bottles. Wooden. Glass bottles with labels, some contents intact.
  - Model of female reproductive tract, undated (Artifact-box 146, Item hwilba0079)
    Raritan, N.J.: Ortho Pharmaceutical Corporation
  - Overbeck's Rejuvenator electrical stimulator, circa 1920s or 1930s (Artifact-box 136, Item hwilba0080)
    Overbeck's Rejuvenator: popular model "Grimsby"; England, O. Overbeck. Housed in box with original instruction book.
  - Royal Army Medical Corps brass buttons, approximately 1860 (Artifact-box 145, Item hwilba0081)
    Six large, two small.
  - Davis - Patent Magneto - Electric Machine for Nervous Diseases, after 1854 (Artifact-box 148, Item hwilba0082)
    New York: W.H. Burnap. Wooden box with magnet and coils, with directions inside lid. Box is damaged and there is no key.
    When handle is turned, it generates current through wires to hand-held cylinders.
  - Hall's New French Battery Electric Stimulator, late 19th century (Artifact-box 147, Item hwilba0083)
    Made in Boston. Wooden box with dry cell battery and electrodes. No key.
  - Replica cuneiform tablet with earliest gynecologic prescription, undated (Artifact-box 135, Item hwilba0084)
  - Two wooden figures of gynecologist and obstetrician, 1950s (Artifact-box 144, Item hwilba0085)
    Sculpted in Germany. Colored.
  - Unglazed stoneware mortar and pestle with wooden handle, undated (Artifact-box 358, Item hwilba0086)
    Size 2 pestle with size 3 extra pestle; wooden handle is loose. Made in U.S.
  - Unidentified wooden handle with threaded metal tip, undated (Box 20, Item hwilba0087)
  - Bowle's stethoscope, early 20th century (Artifact-box 284, Item hwilba0088)
    Early binaural stethoscope. Philadelphia: George P. Pilling & Son Co. In original wooden box.
  - Surgical needle case, undated (Artifact-box 220, Item hwilba0089)
  - Pocket surgical kit, undated (Artifact-box 229, Item hwilba0090)
  - Three pairs of eyeglasses, undated (Artifact-box 211, Item hwilba0091)
    Early eyeglasses; two are in leather cases.
  - Brass balance with weights in tin box, 18th century? (Artifact-box 228, Item hwilba0092)
    Brown tin box is painted orange inside. Contains provenance note, which gives the orginal owner as the Jones Family in New Britain, Connecticut, and dates its use back to 1740.
  - Brass scarificator, undated (Artifact-box 66, Item hwilba0093, Artifact-box 218)
  - Collection of lancets, undated (Artifact-box 359, Item hwilba0094)
    Eight lancets. Four are housed in tortoise sheaths; two are in brass cases with steel blades; one single blade lancet comes with old worn leather case; one triple blade lancet has unusual horn case.
  - Microscope, undated (Artifact-box 210, Item hwilba0095)
    Small brass microscope in wooden box with green lining. Includes a few glass slides, key for outside of case.
  - Microscope (Artifact-box 364, Item hwilba0096)
    Brass microscope in wooden box with handle on top of box. Microscope on wooden moveable stage inscribed Hill and Price, Bristol. Includes a few glass slides.
  - Ivory bell chest piece, undated (Artifact-box 325, Item hwilba0097)
    Chest piece attachment for early stethoscope; the rubber tubing that attached to the chest piece has been lost.
- Robert Williams Collection Artifacts, approximately 1865-1940, 1 items
  Artifacts donated by family of Robert Williams, MD.
  - Cathode ray tube, 20th century (Artifact-box 215, Item hwilli0003)
    Gift of Mrs. Mabel F. Williams in memory of donor's husband, Dr. Robert Williams.
    Received from: Family of Robert Williams, MD
- Anonymous Collection Artifacts, over 85 items
  Medical artifacts received from unknown sources.
  - Spencer dissecting microscope, mid-20th century (Artifact-box 164, Item hanony0001)
    Compound binocular. Signed: Spencer, Buffalo, USA. This example has a pair of metal hand rests.
    One of the first American microscopes was made in 1850 by C.A. and H.R. Spencer of Canastota, New York. Spencer lenses earned a reputation at home and abroad and some experts considered them superior to any European product. Spencer objectives received a Gold Medal at the 1878 Paris Exhibition. The firm subsequently moved to Buffalo in 1890. The complex business history of the firm involved multiple names and leadership changes. In 1935 the Spencer Lens Company was absorbed by the American Optical Company.
    Received from: Unknown source
  - Flea glass, 18th century (Artifact-box 288, Item hanony0003)
    Made of ivory. Essentially a simple magnifier with only one power (7x). Usually the compact design, no larger than the end of a thumb, included a cap or top containing a pin on which to place the specimen and a base with glass discs to serve as "slides" for small objects. Everything screwed together for ease in carrying. Typically, these were used to study tiny insects, hence the name.
  - Acupuncture model, People's Republic of China, 20th century (Artifact-box 153, Item hanony0004)
    Model of the human body showing Chinese acupuncture points and the courses of the meridians. 26 cm tall. Acessories include a case of acupuncture needles and a manual; these are housed in original box.
  - Human skeleton model, articulated, 20th century (Artifact-box 329, Item hanony0005)
    Made of plastic, on stand; 44 cm tall.
    Received from: Purchased by DUMC library
  - Limoges porcelain dish, undated (Artifact-box 117, Item hanony0006)
    Porcelain with gold rim. Colored floral decorations. Large oblong with central cut out along one side and small cut out on one end of the opposite side.
  - Flask and covered jar, undated (Artifact-box 116, Item hanony0007)
    Ruby glass with gold trim. Flask has cork stopper taped to neck.
  - Prosthetic glass eyeballs (Artifact-box 350, Item hanony0008)
    Tray of handblown glass eyeballs in various shades of blue.
  - Pocket ivory thermometer, 19th century (Artifact-box 305, Item hanony0009)
    Includes compass in lid of ivory, velvet-lined case. Engraved on verso of thermometer: Wm Hitchen, 21 Bridgewater Garens [sic]. William Hitchin appears to have been an ivory and tortoiseshell worker at 21 Bridgewater Gardens in the Barbican area of London; he died sometime in 1839 or 1840.
  - Burmese apothecary jar, 19th century? (Artifact-box 184, Item hanony0010)
    Decorated with gilded red lacquer. Design includes central figure surrounded by twelve other figures. Each figure is the lid of a separate cylindrical well for storing herbs and medicinal plants.
    Received from: Purchased from Bary Jones, The Avid Reader
  - Single blade spring lancet in leather case, undated (Artifact-box 9, Item hanony0012)
  - Apothecary jar, undated (Artifact-box 300, Item hanony0013)
    Label: Argent. Oxyd. White ceramic with lid. Lid was damaged and repaired.
  - Apothecary jar, undated (Artifact-box 301, Item hanony0014)
    Label: Hydr. Iod. Rub. White ceramic with lid.
  - Small mortar and pestle, undated (Artifact-box 42, Item hanony0016)
    Marked: Coors, USA.
  - Small ceramic mortar, undated (Artifact-box 308, Item hanony0017)
    White ceramic with pestle missing.
  - Apothecary chest, undated (Item hanony0020)
    Wooden chest with glass knobs, contents of drawers identified with glass labels. Country of origin is England.
  - Anatomical rubber stamps, undated (Artifact-box 244, Item hanony0021)
  - Brass microscope accessories, before 1861 (Artifact-box 213, Item hanony0023)
    Miscellaneous parts, some damaged, housed in wooden box with label: C.T. Amsler, Optician, 635 Chestnut St., Phila. Box has some damage. C.T. Amsler sold his business in Philadelphia in 1861 and returned to Switzerland, his native country.
  - Microscope accessories, undated (Artifact-box 209, Item hanony0024)
    Brass miscroscope accessories housed in wooden cigar box.
  - Surgical instruments, late 19th century (Artifact-box 236, Item hanony0025)
    New York: G. Tiemann & Co. Housed in velvet-lined case.
  - Metal syringe in leather box, undated (Artifact-box 44, Item hanony0026)
    Philadelphia: Chas. Lentz & Sons.
  - Doctor's bag, undated (Artifact-box 234, Item hanony0028)
    Doctor's bag with instruments.
  - Gavel of wood from the birthplace of Walter Reed, undated (Artifact-box 322, Item hanony0029)
    Gavel of wood from the birthplace of Walter Reed, Belroi, Virginia.
  - Caustic pencils, undated (Artifact-box 224, Item hanony0030)
    A caustic pencil is a short stick of medication usually containing silver nitrate, used to cauterize skin, for instance for the treatment of nosebleeds, removal of warts, or pyogenic granuloma. They are not used as a treatment for minor cuts. A frequent source of confusion appears to be the difference between styptic and caustic pencils. Silver nitrate sticks are often used for hemostasis in medical situations where patients are not under general anesthesia, where electrocautery would be painful and inconvenient.
  - Medical instruments in a metal pocket case, 20th century (Artifact-box 226, Item hanony0031)
  - Medical instruments in leather pocket case, undated (Artifact-box 231, Item hanony0032)
  - Medical instruments in leather pocket case, 19th century (Artifact-box 36, Item hanony0033)
    Marked St. Louis, MO: C.W. Alban.
  - Surgical set, undated (Artifact-box 286, Item hanony0034)
    Velvet lined wooden box. Brass plate on lid: Dr. T.B. Fuqua.
  - Tongue depressors, undated (Artifact-box 222, Item hanony0035)
    Package of wooden tongue depressors. Sayah. Original packaging in cardboard box.
  - Petit style tourniquet, 19th century (Artifact-box 63, Item hanony0036)
    Brass with cloth strap.
  - Trephination instruments, 18th-19th centuries (Artifact-box 230, Item hanony0037)
    Hew saw [18th century] and bit [19th century].
  - Brass scale with brass weights, late 19th century? (Artifact-box 225, Item hanony0039)
  - Terra cotta oil lamp, undated (Artifact-box 262, Item hanony0046)
    Early Greek. Replica.
  - Syringe in a metal box, undated (Artifact-box 261, Item hanony0047)
    On plunger knob: D&H, Record. On plunger: Herz, Germany.
  - Silver colored knife, undated (Artifact-box 263, Item hanony0048)
    Metal; possibly used in pill making.
  - Large palette knife, undated (Artifact-box 81, Item hanony0049)
    Used in pill-making. Cast steel with wooden handle.
  - Bell chest piece for Ford stethoscope, early 20th century (Artifact-box 264, Item hanony0051)
    Marked New York: W.F. Ford Co. Brass.
  - Reflex hammer or percussor, undated (Artifact-box 268, Item hanony0052)
  - Hypodermic needle in glass tube, undated (Artifact-box 265, Item hanony0053)
    Hypodermic needle in glass tube
  - Pelvimeter, probe, and curette, undated (Artifact-box 269, Item hanony0054)
  - Wooden test tube stand with six glass test tubes, undated (Artifact-box 344, Item hanony0055)
  - Glass slides of various subjects, undated (Artifact-box 17, Item hanony0057)
  - Mochica medicine man, 20th century (Artifact-box 273, Item hanony0058)
    Schering. Replica of original from Northern Peru, circa 800-1000 AD; replica was used for pharmaceutical advertising.
  - Laennec stethoscope, undated (Artifact-box 173, Item hanony0059)
    Replica of first stethoscope by Rene Theophile Laennec in 1816. Marked "Roche." Housed in gift box.
  - Homeopathic medicine bag, 19th century (Artifact-box 72, Item hanony0060)
    Leather bag with key. Contains 100 labeled glass vials, some with contents: 60 small, 44 large. Also comes with miscellaneous instruments, including metal case with hypodermic needles and lancet.
  - Four different hypodermic devices, undated (Artifact-box 281, Item hanony0061)
    Mounted for display.
  - Obstetrical/gynecological medical instruments, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_1)
    Smellie perforating scissors (right), craniotomy hook (center), and trocar (left).
  - Handle for instrument, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_10)
    Obstetrical/gynecological medical instruments in a wooden box: Handle for instrument, unknown use.
  - Two syringes, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_2)
    Ob/gyn medical instruments in a wooden box: Two syringes marked India Rubber Catarrhal Syringe. Box label reads: manufactured under Goodyear's Patent by India Rubber Comb Company
  - Breast pump, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_3)
    Ob/gyn medical instruments in a wooden box: India rubber breast pump. Box label reads: manufactured under Goodyear's Patent by India Rubber Comb Co.
  - Brass scarificator and set of cups, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_4)
    Ob/gyn medical instruments in a wood box: Brass scarificator, glass cupping jar, and set of graduated metal cups.
  - Rubber pessary, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_5)
    Ob/gyn medical instruments in a wooden box: Rubber pessary
  - Obstetrics forceps, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_6)
    Ob/Gyn medical instruments in a wooden box: Obstetrics forceps with wooden handle, Placenta forceps
  - Speculum, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_7)
    Ob/Gyn medical instruments in a wooden box: Cusco's bivalve speculum, Fergusson's speculum
  - Various probes and catheters, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_8)
    Ob/Gyn medical instruments in a wooden box: various probes and catheters
  - Unidentified instrument, undated (Artifact-box 23, Item hanony0062_9)
    Ob/Gyn medical instruments in a wooden box: Unidentified instrument
  - Miscellaneous medical instruments, undated (Artifact-box 333, Item hanony0063)
    Contents include: Catheters, probes
  - Unidentified medical instrument in brass box (Box 97, Item hanony0067)
    Marked Paris: E.P. [n.d.] Ivory handles.
  - Cast of bound foot with embroidered Chinese shoe, 19th century (Artifact-box 299, Item hanony0069)
    Cast of bound foot of an adult woman treated by Dr. Wm. H. Park around 1890.
    Donated by anonymous patient of Dr. Heidi K. White.
  - Ivory handled surgical instruments, undated (Artifact-box 188, Item hanony0070)
    Set of fourteen surgical instruments with ivory handles.
  - Leather medicine kit, undated (Artifact-box 272, Item hanony0071)
  - Brass microscope, late 19th-early 20th century (Artifact-box 303, Item hanony0073)
    Large brass microscope in wooden case; includes many parts, and specimen slides.
  - Large wooden microscope case with no microscope, undated (Artifact-box 368, Item hanony0074)
  - Wooden box which originally contained obstetrical/gynecological medical instruments, undated (Artifact-box 22, Item hanony0062)